In the summer of 2011, as a tourist,
في صيف عام 2011، كسائح،
I visited the rainforests of Borneo for the very first time,
قمت بزيارة غابات (بورنيو) الاستوائية للمرة الأولى،
and as you might imagine,
وكما قد تتخيلون،
it was the overwhelming sounds of the forest that struck me the most.
فإن الأصوات القوية في تلك الغابة هي أكثر ما جذبني.
There's this constant cacophony of noise.
هناك هذا التنافر المستمر للضوضاء.
Some things actually do stick out.
بعض الأصوات يمكنك تمييزها.
For example, this here is a big bird, a rhinoceros hornbill.
على سبيل المثال، هذا طائر كبير "أبو قرن".
This buzzing is a cicada.
هذا الأزيز للسيكادا.
This is a family of gibbons.
هذه هي عائلة من قرود الجيبون.
It's actually singing to each other over a great distance.
إنها في الواقع تغني لبعضها البعض من مسافة كبيرة.
The place where this was recorded was in fact a gibbon reserve,
المكان الذي سجلت فيه هذه الأصوات كان في الحقيقة أماكن الغيبون،
which is why you can hear so many of them,
وهذا هو السبب أني كنت أسمع الكثير منها،
but in fact the most important noise that was coming out of the forest that time
ولكن في الواقع، الضجيج الأكثر أهمية الذي كان يصدر من الغابة ذلك الوقت
was one that I didn't notice,
كان شيئًا لم ألحظه،
and in fact nobody there had actually noticed it.
في واقع الأمر لا أحد هناك كان قد لاحظه.
So, as I said, this was a gibbon reserve.
لذا، وكما قلت، كانت هذه أماكن الغيبون.
They spend most of their time rehabilitating gibbons,
إنهم يقضون معظم وقتهم في إعادة تأهيل الجيبون،
but they also have to spend a lot of their time
ولكنهم أيضًا يقضون كثيرًا من الوقت
protecting their area from illegal logging that takes place on the side.
في حماية منطقتهم من قطع الأشجار غير القانوني الذي يتم في الخفاء.
And so if we take the sound of the forest
لذا إذا أخذنا صوت الغابة
and we actually turn down the gibbons, the insects, and the rest,
وقمنا بخفض أصوات الغيبون والحشرات وباقي الأصوات،
in the background, the entire time, in recordings you heard,
في الخلفية، وطوال الوقت، في التسجيلات التي سمعناها،
was the sound of a chainsaw at great distance.
كان هناك صوت المنشار يَسمع من مسافة كبيرة.
They had three full-time guards who were posted around this sanctuary
كان لديهم ثلاثة حراس بدوام كامل يتمركزون حول هذه المحمية،
whose job was in fact to guard against illegal logging,
وكانت وظائفهم في الواقع الحراسة ضد قطع الأشجار غير القانوني،
and one day, we went walking, again as tourists, out into the forest,
وفي أحد الأيام كنا نمشي، مرة أخرى كسياح في الغابة،
and within five minutes' walk,
وخلال خمس دقائق من مشينا،
we stumbled upon somebody who was just sawing a tree down,
فوجئنا بشخص كان يقوم بقطع شجرة بالمنشار،
five minutes' walk, a few hundred meters from the ranger station.
على بعد خمس دقائق سيرًا، وبضع مئات من الأمتار من محطة الحارس.
They hadn't been able to hear the chainsaws,
لم يكن باستطاعتهم سماع صوت المناشير،
because as you heard, the forest is very, very loud.
لأنه كما سمعتم، صوت الغابة عالٍ جدًا جدًا.
It struck me as quite unacceptable that in this modern time,
اندهشتُ لأنه ليس من المقبول أنه في هذا العصر،
just a few hundred meters away from a ranger station in a sanctuary,
على بعد بضع مئات من الأمتار من محطة حارس في محمية،
that in fact nobody could hear it when someone who has a chainsaw gets fired up.
أن لا أحد يمكنه سماع شخص لديه منشار يطلق عليه النار.
It sounds impossible, but in fact, it was quite true.
يبدو مستحيلًا، ولكن في الواقع، كان صحيحًا تمامًا.
So how do we stop illegal logging?
كيف لنا وقف قطع الأشجار غير القانوني؟
It's really tempting, as an engineer, always to come up with a high-tech,
ومن المغري حقًا لمهندس أن يصل إلى
super-crazy high-tech solution,
حل تكنولوجي فائق الجنون.
but in fact, you're in the rainforest.
ولكن في الواقع، أنت في غابات مطيرة.
It has to be simple, it has to be scalable,
عليها أن تكون بسيطة، ومتدرجة،
and so what we also noticed while were there was that
وما لاحظناه أيضًا حينما كنا هناك
everything we needed was already there.
ما كنا نحتاجه، كان هناك.
We could build a system that would allow us to stop this
يمكننا أن نبني نظامًا من شأنه أن يسمح لنا بإيقاف هذا
using what's already there.
من خلال استخدام ما هو موجود أصلًا.
Who was there? What was already in the forest?
من كان هناك؟ ماذا كان بالفعل في الغابة؟
Well, we had people.
حسناً، كان لدينا أشخاص.
We had this group there that was dedicated, three full-time guards,
كان لدينا مجموعة متفانية من ثلاثة حراس بدوام كامل
that was dedicated to go and stop it,
مهمتهم أن يوقفوا ذلك،
but they just needed to know what was happening out in the forest.
لكنهم فقط بحاجة إلى معرفة ما كان يحدث في الغابة.
The real surprise, this is the big one,
المفاجأة الحقيقية، وهي شيء كبير،
was that there was connectivity out in the forest.
أنه كان هناك تواصل في الغابة.
There was cell phone service way out in the middle of nowhere.
كانت هناك خدمة الهاتف الخليوي في وسط اللامكان.
We're talking hundreds of kilometers from the nearest road,
نحن نتحدث على بعد مئات الكيلومترات من أقرب طريق،
there's certainly no electricity, but they had very good cell phone service,
بالتأكيد لا توجد كهرباء هناك، لكن خدمة الهاتف الخليوي جيدة جدًا.
these people in the towns were on Facebook all the time,
كان هؤلاء الناس في المدن على الفيسبوك في كل وقت،
they're surfing the web on their phones,
يتصفحون شبكة الانترنت من هواتفهم،
and this sort of got me thinking that in fact it would be possible
وهذا ما أوحى لي بأنه من الممكن
to use the sounds of the forest,
استخدام أصوات الغابة
pick up the sounds of chainsaws programmatically,
لالتقاط الأصوات من المناشير عبر برامج،
because people can't hear them,
لأن الناس لا يمكن أن تسمعها،
and send an alert.
لإرسال تنبيه.
But you have to have a device to go up in the trees.
لكن عليك أن تمتلك جهازًا لتتسلق الأشجار.
So if we can use some device to listen to the sounds of the forest,
لذا إذا كان يمكننا استخدام بعض الأجهزة للاستماع إلى أصوات الغابة
connect to the cell phone network that's there,
ونتصل بشبكة الهاتف الخليوي الموجودة هناك
and send an alert to people on the ground,
ونرسل تنبيهًا للناس على الأرض،
perhaps we could have a solution to this issue for them.
ربما سنجد حلًا لهم لهذه القضية.
But let's take a moment to talk about saving the rainforest,
ولكن دعونا نتوقف لحظة للحديث عن إنقاذ الغابات المطيرة،
because it's something that we've definitely all heard about forever.
لأنه عادة الشيء الذي سمعنا بالتأكيد عنه.
People in my generation have heard about saving the rainforest
سمع الناس في جيلي عن إنقاذ الغابات المطيرة
since we were kids,
منذ كنا صغارًا،
and it seems that the message has never changed:
ويبدو أن الرسالة لم تتغير قط:
We've got to save the rainforest, it's super urgent,
فهمنا أن إنقاذ الغابات المطيرة أمر ملح جدًا،
this many football fields have been destroyed yesterday.
ملاعب كرة القدم هذه تم تدميرها يوم أمس.
and yet here we are today, about half of the rainforest remains,
ولكننا هنا اليوم، وما يقرب من نصف الغابات المطيرة لا تزال موجودة،
and we have potentially more urgent problems like climate change.
ومن المحتمل أن لدينا قضايا أكثر إلحاحًا مثل تغير المناخ.
But in fact, this is the little-known fact that I didn't realize at the time:
ولكن في الواقع، وهذا هو حقيقة غير معروفة لم أكن أدركها في ذلك الوقت:
Deforestation accounts for more greenhouse gas
تفسر إزالة الغابات غازات الاحتباس الحراري
than all of the world's planes, trains, cars, trucks and ships combined.
الأكثر من كل غازات الطائرات والقطارات والسيارات والشاحنات والسفن مجتمعة.
It's the second highest contributor to climate change.
إنها ثاني أكبر مساهم في تغير المناخ.
Also, according to Interpol,
أيضًا، وفقًا للإنتربول،
as much as 90 percent of the logging that takes place in the rainforest
ما يقرب من 90 % من قطع الأشجار الذي يحدث في الغابات المطيرة
is illegal logging, like the illegal logging that we saw.
هو غير قانوني، مثل قطع الأشجار غير القانوني الذي رأيناه.
So if we can help people in the forest enforce the rules that are there,
إذا استطعنا مساعدة الناس في الغابة في فرض القواعد الموجودة هناك،
then in fact we could eat heavily into this 17 percent
من الممكن أن نستهلك كثيرًا في هذه الـ 17 %
and potentially have a major impact in the short term.
ويحتمل أن يكون لها تأثير كبير على المدى القصير.
It might just be the cheapest, fastest way to fight climate change.
قد تكون أرخص، واسرع وسيلة لمكافحة تغير المناخ.
And so here's the system that we imagine.
و هنا هو النظام الذي كنا نتصوره.
It looks super high tech.
تكنولوجيا فائقة.
The moment a sound of a chainsaw is heard in the forest,
لحظة سماع صوت المنشار في الغابة،
the device picks up the sound of the chainsaw,
يلتقط الجهاز الصوت.
it sends an alert through the standard GSM network that's already there
ويرسل تنبيهًا من خلال شبكة جي إس إم الموجودة هناك
to a ranger in the field
إلى الحارس في المحطة
who can in fact show up in real time and stop the logging.
الذين يمكن أن يظهر في الوقت المناسب ويوقف قطع الأشجار.
It's no more about going out and finding a tree that's been cut.
إن الأمر لا يزيد عن الخروج والعثور على شجرة تم قطعها.
It's not about seeing a tree from a satellite
إنها ليست حول رؤية شجرة من الأقمار الصناعية
in an area that's been clear cut,
في منطقة واضحة المعالم،
it's about real-time intervention.
ولكنه عن التدخل في الوقت المناسب.
So I said it was the cheapest and fastest way to do it,
لذلك قلت أنه أرخص وأسرع طريقة للقيام بذلك،
but in fact, actually, as you saw, they weren't able to do it,
ولكن في الواقع، وكما رأيتم، لم يكونوا قادرين على القيام بذلك،
so it may not be so cheap and fast.
لذلك قد لا تكون رخيصة وسريعة جدًا.
But if the devices in the trees were actually cell phones,
ولكن إذا كانت الأجهزة في الأشجار هواتف محمولة،
it could be pretty cheap.
يمكن أن تكون رخيصة جدًا.
Cell phones are thrown away by the hundreds of millions every year,
يتم رمي الهواتف المحمولة من قبل مئات الملايين كل عام،
hundreds of millions in the U.S. alone,
مئات الملايين في الولايات المتحدة وحدها،
not counting the rest of the world, which of course we should do,
ناهيك عن بقية العالم، والتي بالطبع ينبغي لنا أن نحصيها.
but in fact, cell phones are great.
ولكن في الواقع، الهواتف الخلوية رائعة.
They're full of sensors.
كلها أجهزة استشعار
They can listen to the sounds of the forest.
يمكن أن تسمتع إلى أصوات الغابة.
We do have to protect them.
ينبغي علينا حمايتها.
We have to put them in this box that you see here,
علينا أن نضعها في هذا الصندوق الذي ترونه هنا،
and we do have to power them.
وعلينا أن نشغلها.
Powering them is one of the greater engineering challenges
يعد تشغيلها واحدة من أكبر التحديات الهندسية
that we had to deal with,
التي علينا التعامل معها،
because powering a cell phone under a tree canopy,
لأن تشغيل الهاتف الخليوي تحت مظلة شجرة،
any sort of solar power
وأي نوع من الطاقة الشمسية
was an as-yet-unsolved problem,
تعد مشكلة لم تحل بعد،
and that's this unique solar panel design that you see here,
وهذا تصميم فريد للوحة للطاقة الشمسية التي تروها هنا،
which in fact is built also from recycled byproducts of an industrial process.
وهي في الواقع مبنية أيضُا من إعادة تدوير لمنتجات عملية صناعية.
These are strips that are cut down.
هذه هي الشرائط التي يتم قطعها.
So this is me putting it all together
وهذا أنا أقوم بتجميعها
in my parents' garage, actually.
في مرآب والدايّ، في الواقع.
Thanks very much to them for allowing me to do that.
شكرًا جزيلًا لهم لإتاحة الفرصة لي للقيام بذلك.
As you can see, this is a device up in a tree.
كما ترون، ها هو الجهاز أعلى الشجرة.
What you can see from here, perhaps, is that they are pretty well obscured
ما ترونه من هنا، ربما، هو أنه تم اخفائه بشكل جيد
up in the tree canopy at a distance.
أعلى في ظلة شجرة من مسافة بعيدة.
That's important, because although they are able to hear chainsaw noises
هذا أمر مهم، لأنه على الرغم من قدرتهم على سماع الأصوات المنشار
up to a kilometer in the distance,
على بعد كيلومتر واحد
allowing them to cover about three square kilometers,
مما يسمح لهم تغطية حوالي ثلاثة كيلومترات مربعة،
if someone were to take them, it would make the area unprotected.
إذا كان شخص ما سيقوم بأخذهم، من شأنه أن يجعل المنطقة غير محمية.
So does it actually work?
لذا هل هذا حل جيد؟
Well, to test it, we took it back to Indonesia,
حسنا، لاختباره، أعدناه إلى إندونيسيا،
not the same place, but another place,
لا لنفس المكان، ولكن الى مكان آخر،
to another gibbon reserve
إلى محمية جيبون أخرى
that was threatened daily by illegal logging.
مهددة يوميًا بقطع الأشجار غير القانوني.
On the very second day, it picked up illegal chainsaw noises.
في اليوم الثاني، التقط الجهاز ضجة المنشار.
We were able to get a real-time alert.
وحصلنا على تنبيه في الوقت المناسب.
I got an email on my phone.
وصلني بريد إلكتروني على هاتفي.
Actually, we had just climbed the tree. Everyone had just gotten back down.
في الواقع، كنا قد صعدنا الشجرة للتو. وكان الجميع قد نزل.
All these guys are smoking cigarettes,
كل هؤلاء الرجال يدخنون السجائر،
and then I get an email, and they all quiet down,
ثم تحصلت على البريد الإلكتروني، وركد الجميع.
and in fact you can hear the chainsaw
في واقع الأمر يمكنك أن تسمع المنشار
really, really faint in the background,
خافت جدًا جدًا في الخلفية،
but no one had noticed it until that moment.
ولكن لا أحد قد لاحظ ذلك حتى تلك اللحظة.
And so then we took off to actually stop these loggers.
وحين ذهبنا لوقف قاطعي الأشجار.
I was pretty nervous.
كنت عصبيًا جدًا.
This is the moment where we've actually arrived close to where the loggers are.
هذه هي اللحظة التي تمكنا فيها من الوصول على مقربة منهم.
This is the moment where you can see where I'm actually regretting
هذه هي اللحظة التي تراني فيها نادمًا
perhaps the entire endeavor.
ربما عن المحاولة برمتها.
I'm not really sure what's on the other side of this hill.
لست متأكدًا حقًا مما يدور في الجانب الآخر من هذا التل.
That guy's much braver than I am.
هذا الرجل أكثر شجاعة مني.
But he went, so I had to go, walking up,
ولكنه ذهب، فاضطررت للصعود،
and in fact, he made it over the hill,
ونجح هو في الوصول الى التل
and interrupted the loggers in the act.
وقاطع عمل قاطعي الأشجار.
For them, it was such a surprise --
بالنسبة لهم، كانت هذه مفاجأة -
they had never, ever been interrupted before --
لم يقاطع أحد عملهم من قبل.
that it was such an impressive event for them,
وكان هذا مثار إعجاب لهم
that we've heard from our partners they have not been back since.
حيث سمعنا من شركائنا أنهم لم يعودوا منذ ذلك الحين.
They were, in fact, great guys.
كانوا، في الواقع، رجالًا عظماء.
They showed us how the entire operation works,
إنها أظهرت لنا كيف تعمل العملية برمتها،
and what they really convinced us on the spot was that
وما كان مقنعًا لنا على الفور هو أنه
if you can show up in real time and stop people,
لو كنت بإمكانك الظهور في الوقت المناسب وإيقافهم،
it's enough of a deterrent they won't come back.
فيكفي هذا كرادع لهم بعدم المعاودة.
So --
إذًا.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا.
Word of this spread, possibly because we told a lot of people,
انتشر الأمر، ربما لأننا أخبرنا الكثير من الناس،
and in fact, then some really amazing stuff started to happen.
وفي الحقيقة، بعض الأشياء المدهشة بدأت بالحدوث.
People from around the world started to send us emails, phone calls.
بدأ الناس من جميع أنحاء العالم بإرسال الرسائل الإلكترونية والاتصال هاتفيًا.
What we saw was that people throughout Asia,
ما رأيناه هو أن الناس في جميع أنحاء آسيا،
people throughout Africa, people throughout South America,
وفي جميع أنحاء أفريقيا، وفي جميع أنحاء أمريكا الجنوبية،
they told us that they could use it too,
أخبرونا أن بإمكانهم استخدامها أيضًا،
and what's most important,
والأهم من ذلك
what we'd found that we thought might be exceptional,
أننا وجدنا أن ما كنا نظنه استثنائيًا
in the forest there was pretty good cell phone service.
أن في الغابة خدمة هاتف خلوي جيدة جدًا،
That was not exceptional, we were told,
قيل لنا أن ذلك لم يكن استثنائيًا،
and that particularly is on the periphery of the forests that are most under threat.
وهذا بوجه خاص على هامش الغابات الأكثر عرضة للخطر.
And then something really amazing happened,
ثم حدث شيء مدهش حقًا،
which was that people started sending us their own old cell phones.
كان في إرسال الناس لهواتفهم المحمولة القديمة.
So in fact what we have now is a system
في الواقع ما لدينا الآن هو نظام
where we can use people on the ground, people who are already there,
حيث يمكننا استخدام الناس على الأرض، الناس الذين هم بالفعل هناك،
who can both improve and use the existing connectivity,
الذين يستطيعون تحسين واستخدام شبكة التواصل القائمة،
and we're using old cell phones that are being sent to us
نستخدم الآن الهواتف القديمة التي يرسلها الناس
by people from around the world
من جميع أنحاء العالم
that want their phones to be doing something else in their afterlife,
والذين يريدون أن تقوم هواتفهم بشيء آخر في حياتها الأخرى.
so to speak.
إن صح التعبير.
And if the rest of the device can be completely recycled,
وإذا كان بالامكان إعادة تدوير بقية الأجهزة بالكامل،
then we believe it's an entirely upcycled device.
فستكون أجهزة جديدة تمامًا.
So again, this didn't come because of any sort of high-tech solution.
ومرة أخرى، لم يحدث هذا نتيجة للتكنولوجيا الفائقة.
It just came from using what's already there,
بل من استخدام ما هو متاح هناك،
and I'm thoroughly convinced that if it's not phones,
وأنا مقتنع تمامًا أنه إن لم تكن الهواتف،
that there's always going to be enough there
فسيكون هناك دائمًا ما يكفي
that you can build similar solutions
لإيجاد حلول مماثلة
that can be very effective in new contexts.
يمكنها أن تكون فعالة جدًا في سياقات جديدة.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.